<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="5.1">
   <title>p:urify</title>
  <para><code>p:urify()</code> is a function that attempts to transform file system paths into file URIs. If a URI is already
    given as an argument, it should pass it unchanged, apart from character escaping and slash contractions that are permitted
    for (presumptive) file URIs.</para>
  <para>The function may be implemented as an operation on strings; it need not try to determine the existence of a file or
    directory, it should not follow symbolic links, etc. How the function performs the task is implementation-dependent.</para>
  <para>The purpose of this function is to resolve a file system path to a URI on the platform that the processor runs on; the
    function need not resolve, for example, Windows paths when the processor runs on a Unix-like operating system. The function
    is intended as a pure convenience for pipeline authors and users for transforming OS specific paths and paths relative to
    the working directory from which they invoked the processor. </para>
  <para>The function aims at supporting Unix-like (for example, Linux, Solaris, Mac OS X) and Windows file system paths.
    Operating systems with other filesystem path addressing schemes (for example, VMS or Mac OS) need not be supported.</para>
  <methodsynopsis>
    <type>xs:string</type>
    <methodname>p:urify</methodname>
    <methodparam><type>xs:string</type><parameter>filepath</parameter></methodparam>
    <methodparam><type>xs:string?</type><parameter>basedir</parameter></methodparam>
  </methodsynopsis>
  <para>Each argument may be an operating system path, including UNC paths on Windows, or a URI. The function need not guarantee
    that an argument identified as a URI is a <emphasis>correct</emphasis> URI. It may attempt to correct errors in purported
    file URIs, such as fixing the missing escaping of a space character. It should leave non-file URIs unchanged.</para>
  <para>If the <code>$basedir</code> argument is omitted or is the empty sequence, the current working directory should  be used
    if available. The <code>$basedir</code> argument or the current working directory will only be considered if the
      <code>$filepath</code> is determined to be relative.</para>
  <note>
    <para>Sometimes file names are created in an encoding that does not match the system’s locale. This function does not aim at
      solving these issues. Implementations should not try to correct apparent errors that originate from garbled encodings
      since they will probably not be able to produce file URIs that address the corresponding files correctly.</para>
    <para>Likewise it is also possible, in particular on Windows, that the encoding gets garbled when command line arguments are
      passed to  </para>
  </note>
  <section>
    <title>Access to the Environment</title>
    <para>The function needs access to the following information that the implementation would return for the
        <code>p:os-info</code> step.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>file-separator (<code>xs:string</code>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The path separator, typically '/' on Unix and '\' on Windows. If none can be determined, '/' will be assumed. </para>
          <para>The forward slash is a valid path separator for the <code>filepath</code> argument even when the system’s
              <code>file-separator</code> is '\'.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>os-name (<code>xs:string?</code>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the operating system, for example 'Mac OS X'.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>cwd (<code>xs:string?</code>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The current working directory, that is, the directory from which the processor was invoked.</para>
          <para>It may not be available if the pipeline or processor was not invoked from a working directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Operating System Path Syntax</title>
    <para>The <firstterm>operating system path syntax</firstterm> is said to be of type “Windows” if at least one of the
      following conditions is satisfied: <code>os-name</code> starts with 'Windows' or <code>file-separator</code>
      is '\'.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Classification of the arguments</title>
    <para>After finding out which operating system path syntax to expect on the current platform, the function determines the
      types of its arguments, starting with the <code>$filepath</code> argument. The <code>$basedir</code> argument (or
        <code>cwd</code>) need only be classified and normalized if <code>$filepath</code> is determined to be relative.</para>
    <para>Each argument is supposed to be either a file system path or already a URI. The arguments (including <code>cwd</code>)
      need not be of the same type; one can be an OS path and the other one a URI.</para>
    <para>The distinction between file system paths and URIs is too coarse-grained though for this function’s string
      manipulation rules. </para>
    <para>The first of the following conditions that is met will determine the argument’s detailed type:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^[a-z]:[\\/]+</code> and if the OS path syntax is of
          type “Windows”, it is determined to be an absolute Windows path with a drive letter.</para>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^[a-z]:([^\\/]|$)</code> and if the OS path syntax is of type
          “Windows”, a dynamic error is thrown because relative paths with a drive letter are not supported by this
          function.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument starts with two backslashes, followed by a string that may serve as a host name,
          followed by a forward or backward slash, and if the OS path syntax type is “Windows”, it is determined to be a UNC
          path.</para>
        <para>For simplification purposes, an approximate regular expression of <code>[a-z0-9][-.a-z0-9]*</code> may be used to
          match a possible host name part. An implementation is free to use a more accurate regular expression.</para>
        <para>This regular expression will also match IPv6 addresses that are escaped for UNC paths according to
          https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20100915-00/?p=12863/<remark> (move into bibliography section)</remark>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^file:(/|/{3,})?[a-z]:/+</code> and if the OS path
          syntax is of type “Windows”, it is determined to be the file URI of an absolute Windows path with a drive
          letter.</para>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^file:(/|/{3,})?[a-z]:([^/]|$)</code> and if the OS path
          syntax is of type “Windows”, a dynamic error is thrown because relative paths with a drive letter are not
          supported.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^file:(//|/{4,})[a-z\d][-.a-z\d]*/+</code> (possibly
          with a more accurate regular expression for the hostname part, see the “UNC path” type above) and if the OS path
          syntax is of type “Windows”, it is determined to be the file URI of a Windows UNC path.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^file:[^/]</code>, it is determined to be a
          relative file URI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^file:/+</code>, it is determined to be an
          absolute file URI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^//[a-z\d][-.a-z\d]*/</code> (or a more elaborate hostname
          regex), it will be interpreted as a same-protocol URL and passed unchanged, even on Windows where it could be
          interpreted as a protocol-agnostic UNC URI. The rationale is to treat the relatively widespread case of
            <code>http:</code>/<code>https:</code> agnostic URLs gracefully even if the pipeline author passes every potential
          URI or filesystem path through <code>p:urify()</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches the regular expression <code>^/+</code>, it is determined to be an absolute OS path. If it
          is an absolute Windows path and if there is a drive letter is in the <code>basedir</code>/<code>cwd</code> argument,
          the drive letter will be inserted later on.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the argument matches <code>^[a-z][-+.0-9a-z]*:</code> (a URI scheme as defined in RFC 3986, followed
          by a colon), it is determined as a non-file URI.</para>
        <para>An implementation may perform more thorough checks against the syntax specification of RFC 3986 and raise
          a warning if the URI is non-conforming.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Any other argument value will be interpreted as a relative path or URI.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>If the argument is determined to be a file URI, the argument will further be classified as escapable or non-escapable.
        <termdef>A file URI is <firstterm>escapable</firstterm> if it contains other characters than those that match the
        regular expression <code>-._~[a-z]\d:/\?#\[\]@!$&amp;'\(\)\*\+,;=</code> (the reserved and unreserved characters in RFC
        3986, plus the percent character)</termdef>. Such a URI is technically not a valid URI. However, it happens in practice
      that users try to turn OS paths into file URIs by simply prepending <code>file:</code> (or <code>file:/</code> for Windows
      forward-slash paths) without thinking about hex-escaping spaces and other special characters. In order to be useful also
      in these circumstances, the function will escape path components, query strings, and fragment identifiers in escapable
      file URIs using <code>fn:encode-for-uri()</code> (see below).</para>
    <para>An OS path is always escapable which means that its path components after slash tokenization will be escaped using
        <code>fn:encode-for-uri()</code>.</para>
    <para>If <code>$basedir</code> is given and if it is identified as a relative OS path or file URI, a dynamic error is
      thrown.</para>
    <para>If no <code>$basedir</code> is given and <code>cwd</code> is unavailable, a dynamic error is thrown for relative
        <code>filepath</code> paths/URIs.</para>
  </section>  
  <section>
    <title>Normalization Steps</title>
    <para>Then the function performs the steps listed below on <code>$filepath</code>.</para>
    <para>It will also normalize <code>$basedir</code> in the same way if <code>$filepath</code> is determined to be relative.</para>
    <para>If <code>$filepath</code> is relative and no <code>$basedir</code> is given, <code>cwd</code> is subjected to the same
      normalization steps. Of course this <code>cwd</code> normalization needs to be done only once if the processor stores the
      result internally.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If <code>$filepath</code> is a relative file URI, <code>^file:</code> will be removed and it will be treated like
          other relative paths.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the operating system path syntax is of type “Windows”, backslashes will be converted to forward
        slashes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If resulting string is determined to be a file URI, its scheme information will be converted to lower
          case (<code>file</code>).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The argument will be split into a prefix part and a remainder part. The prefix will hold everything that is
            '<code>file:</code>', slashes, drive letters, and host names, excluding the last slash that follows these
          components. The remainder part then starts with a single slash, or no slash for relative arguments.</para>
        <para>For URI arguments, the remainder part will be further split into a path part, a query part (starting with '?'),
          and a fragment part (starting with '#'), according to RFC 3986, Sect. 3.</para>
        <para>Query or fragment parts stemming from <code>basedir</code> will be disregarded.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The resulting path part will be tokenized at <code>/+</code>. Tokens that are empty or that are <code>.</code>
          (current directory) will be removed from the sequences, except for a single leading and a single trailing empty token,
          if present, corresponding to leading and trailing slashes, respectively.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hex escaping: If the argument is escapable, each token in the sequence will be replaced by its
            <code>fn:encode-for-uri()</code> value.</para>
        <para>In the query and fragments parts of escapable URIs, the reserved and unreserved characters such as '=', ';', and
          '&amp;' must be excluded from hex escaping. Apart from these characters, the parts will be hex escaped if and only if
          the URI is escapable. </para>
        <para>OS paths never have query or fragment components, therefore <code>fn:encode-for-uri()</code> will be applied to
          each split-at-slash token.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The path part sequences that stem from <code>$filepath</code> and, if present, those that stem from
            <code>$basedir</code> or <code>cwd</code> will be combined so that the <code>$filepath</code> subsequence comes
          last. Duplicate empty tokens at the joint will be contracted into a single one.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Parent path contraction: Processing the tokens from left to right, for every group of <code>..</code> tokens the
          same number of preceding tokens (or all preceding tokens if there are less preceding tokens than adjacent parent path
          tokens) will be removed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The path tokens will be re-assembled with each empty token replaced with a slash ('/').</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the stored prefix part, lower-case drive letters of Windows OS paths or file URIs will be converted to
          upper-case. </para>
        <para>Host names in the prefix (UNC paths/URIs) will be converted to lower-case.</para>
        <para>Multiple slashes before the host name in UNC file URIs will be reduced to '//' (two slashes).</para>
        <para>A single or more than three slashes in drive letter file URIs will be replaced with exactly three slashes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the prefix stems from an OS path, <code>file://</code> will be prepended for Unix paths, <code>file:///</code>
          for Windows drive letter paths and <code>file:</code> for Windows UNC paths.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Query and fragment parts of the <code>filepath</code> URI argument will be appended, with the '?' and '#'
          separators re-inserted if they were present in the argument.</para>
      </listitem>      
      <listitem>
        <para>The prefix will be prepended.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>  
  <section>
    <title>Errors</title>
    <para>It is a dynamic error if <code>$filepath</code> is determined to be relative, no <code>$basedir</code> is
    given that can be transformed into an absolute URI and <code>cwd</code> information is unavailable.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Testing</title>
    <para>Depending on the system where the tests run on, the results may vary. For example, an implementation may add a
      trailing slash to the file URI if it recognizes that it represents a directory.</para>
    <para>One way to make the test results more predictable is to provide an additional function argument that holds a map with
      certain overriding parameters, such as the <code>file-separator</code> or whether the <code>filepath</code> argument
      represents a directory. However, this is impractical if the implementation relies on external libraries to perform the
      conversion.</para>
    <para>A test suite may therefore specify system-dependent tests that run only on Windows or Linux and that accept function
      results with or without a trailing slash.</para>
  </section>   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
</section>
